Hello, welcome to the next episode of Learn German in Hindi.
Today we are going to
learn one of the most important German
constructions. I have
seen many people who
come to me and say that they understand all the other German bad
behavior, but they do
n't understand the use of 'der', the use of 'tanu', the use of 'dam'. The main
reason for this is that they are not learnt systematically,
but today we are going to learn it by understanding it in a very simple way
and I will tell you
that when today's video ends,
you will understand how it is used and
how to use it. By the way,
this concept is a bit big and we are
also going to cover prepositions in it, so that is why
we have made three lessons for it, but after this lesson
you will understand it completely. So let's
start. First of all, is it case case? The
inflections that everyone speaks in simple Hindi,
how are they in German? In Hindi, you have seen
first, second, third, fourth, such persons are there even today.
This character has given a character to a
character, these are all persons.  What does it do to
whom does it belong to the name or the
pronoun and what does it teach that
your name, this pronoun,
what does it do in that sentence, what is its function, does it do, is it the object
or is it the
indirect object, it
explains the problems, it is the same in German also, there are
only four persons in German, there are 34 in it, so
we do not use it much
and we learn it only after the amazing to,
so we have to learn only three,
just three nominatives, you tune in and put it, it is
simple, isn't it,
first let us see that the nominative, the two
names seem very big, is it very
simple, if you
use your name in any sentence,
means subject, then you put in the
nominative, okay, means Kedar eats mango, who
eats mango, the character, so here the nominative is what he eats, he eats mango, so what is mango,
Karan, so he does it while improving, so he has
zodiac signs, action, so there are some complex and such
sentences in it and  One thing has to be done,
it is called communication in Hindi or
indirect object in English.
Kedar performed the OV. Who is the subject, character,
who is the object, what is the
indirect object? This indirect
object is dirty, very simple. So, the
fear of big boys is gone. If you
feel that you are the subject, then you are nominative.
If you are the object, then you are your duty.
And if you are the indirect object, then you are
afraid. Very simple. Okay, now we can do a little bit.
Now this is very good. Which is
my favorite because it is the same as our
Hindi. So, what is it that in English,
if you see, the gender of all the inanimate
objects becomes
speechless,
but it is not like that in our Hindi,
we have given masculine and feminine gender to inanimate objects as well,
like my book or
my room. It is the same in German too, that these are
good inanimate objects which will be
roasted by the garden, hence it has been made neutral. Now, there are
two things to be kept in mind in this, first of all, it is
my favorite. That's it, more on that front.  Truck, bus
and truck are both in English, the
size, weight and mode of both are same but bus has been
made girl, feeling and
truck has been made open, bus comes, truck
comes, why did we not ask, we did
not ask or why my book, why my room, we
never asked, similarly in German also the
gender of any inanimate object is female
or neutral, there is no
middle meaning in asking why it is there,
Sanjay Dutt, second thing
means I myself know Marathi also, so the word '
ghaddi' in Hindi is feminine,
but the same 'ghaddi' becomes 'ghaddi' neutral in Marathi,
this term becomes, till now there are
so many words in Marathi,
both come from Sanskrit, the script of both is
same, still the thing which is feminine in Hindi will
become neuter in German, so if something comes
to Hindi and is of feminine gender, then it will be of
masculine gender in German, it is wrong to expect such thing,
understand these two simple things, just
like Hindi, in Germany also
inanimate objects can have different genders
and the Hindi channel is born  Yes, I did
not understand this necessarily, I will explain
more, that is why a lot of people make the
mistake of saying that
hello, you are learning
German, you are learning new words, so along with that,
learn the gender of the word, you will meet many people like this or
you will see on some websites that if there is an end, then
it is feminine, but there is
no fun in all those shortcuts, if you are
learning a language, then you should
learn it with respect, so
what will we do when we learn a new word, we will
learn along with its gender, so this is the first thing
you have to understand, what is the nominative word,
what is its role in your sentence, and
your keyword is it, it can be masculine,
feminine, or neutral, this is
something, if it is clear, then now we will learn
actually how to use it,
basically without the word, what is this piece, we will
learn what
your letter is in English,
what is the different article, the definitive meaning,
do I know what it is when the
boy, if we all know now in English,
whatever the word is, it is the same  If it is very much then
that angle is also certain and even if there is a baby then
also Dutt is not like this in German,
in German it becomes the form of two,
how are they made of pain rate, so the first thing
we learned is that the unknown has worked in the sentence
and two,
he himself is responsible whether he makes the payment or not, so
we will learn that with the help of a table,
this ice will be visible above, it is very simple,
I say this idea is very simple, it is
like fifth grade math, just look at
a tablet 354 and a table, give it two extensions,
so this table is important, first
if you look at it, what is the masculine and feminine
not rule or plural, meaning
male-female not Ramya plural, now the good thing is
that I take that
its camera, which it will
always do the same Chetak, then it does not have,
then we do
not need to look at the rest of the three things, so on one access it is done
male-female Newton plural, secondly
what is on this, secondly what is its work,
no my tablet does it according to and  If it is an
indirect object then time this
triphala fontan I understood three four table
now the content from it that you are going to use it so many times that
you will easily remember it, it becomes
your minister, he will
learn the accident let's chant the mantra once let's
say with me
the wash the wash
220 without being dam drop middle aged now
how to use it we request you to
share the paper with me then
we will make a sentence how to do it in the center let's take the
first sentence before that let's
learn four words of German which will be
easy for us first one is ball or birth
it is called hair wash this was
voice mail masculine song in German
that aval means watch we have learnt it
is feminine in German
hello how to we know this alto means
car again look come to install and toning
gola whatever you write you will say the same now tong to
neutral and its plural becomes altos
altos and let's learn another word road meaning
red red so it is easy for us to make sentences
Generally we start making sentences,
you do Vishnu with me, ok eat
and then I always tell every batch, I will tell you the
same thing, always follow these steps
when you judge, as I have studied
German for six-seven years, okay then I
can delete it from the road, but when you are new, do
not forget to do it step by step, whatever you do step by step,
or you have always done it, you will make a
mistake, spoon step by
step, okay let's start, the God is
great, the ball is red, then here we have to
replace it, now
we will find it below it, now say this dhaappa,
what is the next thing in this sentence, what is it, does it
mean subject, so
you will write S8 below it and subject, and if it is
subject, then which gas is nominated, you will
write nominated, and what is the game itself, male
pulling wet in German, then you will
write a splash and slash and ok and
your table cigarette, you see in it, what is
nominative male, intersection, that is why it has become one and
a half ball destroyed, very
simple and after all  If you do this you will understand
next when we take more things then the center
line will be 1000 it will be again hard here the
subject is SN for Mummy Natyam and
what is the watch itself female in German that is why
splash tense lab and what is the nominative price
see it has appeared so
what will happen wall till this treatment simple
work period we will add Prem Agni Dakshin channel
subject nominative work
neutral nominative neutral our
teeth teeth toe has been destroyed
[music]
12th pass so we are working next car has
become plural so what will you
write below it subject nominative loot and
what is nominated that is why it will be Di
Awadhesh Singh Road because there is nothing in the road
its answer is work and its
gender is looking at its mode off now let
us do it so that is why call again do it
now check it that is why it is
and the tumor itself is that
this news de Rabba Ishq Khabar Daily understood
everyone first fear rather that subject is that way
come  Yes, we will watch again the doctor
line and check Akoda why the female
voice mail is Akunth husband, that's why this yes,
Badi Mor is
a special he ran again to the southern
channel and lokay you will get the result you know
trump trump what is the this chapter
claim thok kar kar he has come another car
i20 car below lines of account this is something like this too
simple right, what
you have to do is two actresses have
worked on access, she has done it herself,
just add access you will get your table
now the third one which we saw the character
tied Omi in it is obd2 there are
very few such sentences in any language
so what we will do is hmm we will do it in a more simple
way so the prepositions in German, the
prepositions on that side it appears that is
why it can be
2030 that's why till now the
position is fine, no we will
learn prepositions in the third class of this so
then the most important preposition that we will
learn today is with with means when mind
I said
okay, so this is the position of doctors, so the
position of doctors means
what will happen after this, whatever comes, we will
make a tube, it is clear, so let us try it,
I will play with the ball is a place
with above all fronts, we will do the parties, we have
landed in Noida, now see,
before that the daughter had come, so that is why we will
deport and it has definitely been done, so
what will happen in that, look
in your table, dam, this thing, pain killer, minute, dum,
boil, if you see all three sentences, the first
time, what was it, well, hair straight, then
wish, love, day after, and now it happened, this
pillar, minute, Demba, drawn, it kept changing, why did it
not change like this, because his hair color can
change in that sentence, it is
clear to everyone, now we will see the next sentence, did he
understand this sentence, kiss him, let me
play with what is placed,
grab the calling, first what is with, so
digestive dip, watch what is female, do
female, go and see for
some time, that is why there will be love limit
Why is it most popular here on cross because
many people have a habit of
learning new things by doing uniforms, so this comes to
their mind, so here they definitely
keep how to make about them,
understand that time is the form of male-female
digestive, that is why I will always do it, if you want to remember that
female SSC
milk, then always remember it,
understood, I am a woman, so here we are saying,
in this sequence, understood, on Thursday, let's go to the
questions, if Balkar
wash, again with, due to dip, lash,
depression, again, Dhoom, speed
limit, dam, how to all, Dual, let's come again,
what will you do with IPL medicine,
which is the channel live with, so
tune in, Floral, do, Floral, Dahan, Ishq,
Pillar, Midday, Altos, Simple, Accused, you must be
seeing these sentences of Shanti
everywhere, Uddin is seen, how did we do this, so
his work is, he does, he is
with vid, and he is Megh, and we do it
step by step, there is nothing to
understand  I have come, I will tell everyone
that today you should understand these sentences properly, in the
next class when we learn in express,
I will give some more words and their
masculine and feminine forms, then you will be able to do it,
but today I do not want to confuse you much, so what
you should do is, today let's
start, thank you, they are very good,
okay, that concept and understand these 12
sentences, how do you understand 80 percent, in the
next class,
in the next class we will learn more Buddha messages,
and then as for you, we will learn how to use it,
okay, so that video, I will
upload it every two days, if you want to
watch this video and if you want to know
when that video is coming, then I
request you to please subscribe to my channel
and click on the bell icon,
as when I upload a new video,
you will get a notification, so as
I said, I request you again to
write all these 12 sentences on paper,
watch them calmly, today we have learnt the basic
shots,
we will take it forward in the next class, see you
in the next class, dear